<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>ciwise.com</title>
   
   <link>http://ciwise.com</link>
   <description>Your Dreams. Our Design.</description>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <managingEditor> David L. Whitehurst</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Welcome to CI Wise</title>
	  <link>//welcome-to-ci-wise</link>
	  <author>David L. Whitehurst</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-01T10:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//welcome-to-ci-wise</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Welcome to CI Wise. We're dedicated to being a company that's focused on helping start-ups and smaller enterprises be world-class. Are you wise to Continuous Improvement practices? Every successful business is on a quest to be better. Our job is to help you get there using open source and economical architectural solutions. This is our specialty. Your dreams can be our designs. You can operate your IT and Software infrastructure just like the bigger, more capitalized corporations. That's the environment we were trained in. With education, there are ways to do things without the purchase of expensive third-party software. We're here to inform you e.g. you can run an enterprise service bus and integrate your software as a service (SaaS) applications. You can can execute your batch operations beyond extensive script processing. It's possible to enter the Microservice arena with minimal investment. We can design solid solutions for you. Tell us more, we're here to help. We're here to serve you.</p>





	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Security Consideration and Lifestyle Exchange (SCALE)</title>
	  <link>//security-consideration-and-lifestyle-exchange</link>
	  <author>David L. Whitehurst</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-06-25T07:01:00-04:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//security-consideration-and-lifestyle-exchange</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h3>Introduction</h3>
<p>It is my firm belief that developers today are not focused on security during periods of head-down
development. I would love to know the percentage of web developers that know about the Open Web
Application Security Project or OWASP. This non-profit organization is simply focused on the secure
development of web applications. Their education and guidance is freely available to the public yet I do
not read much about security in the public development circles, blogs, etc.</p>

<p>OWASP first published a book called the Code Review Guide in 2006. In 2006, I led a team on the
development of a large web application for the administration of the Women, Infants, and Children
(WIC) program for the state of Massachusetts. We were doing weekly code reviews and our focus was
on best practice and quality development of the software. Quality code is secure code.</p>

<p>OWASP had noticed in their 2006 publication where organizations had implemented a proper code
review function into their software development lifecycle (SDLC), they enjoyed remarkably better
code from a security perspective. The team code review does not, however guarantee a security
consideration or security focus on the architecture, designs, patterns, or methods being implemented.
This consideration must come from the developers themselves.</p>

<h3>Urgency</h3>
<p>Throughout my career I have strived to create a sense of urgency where I have had the authority to
bring about change in the organization. As a business owner, I receive about 10-15 whitepapers from
various sources daily covering many IT subjects but most of these papers are communicating the need
for more security in our IT infrastructures, products and services, on-premise or off. The education and
intelligence of sorts is mostly marketing by organizations to provide security tools or consulting with
the promise to make my business more secure. They are creating the sense of urgency here by using the
psychology of fear in their publications.
</p>
<p>Security of IT infrastructure, products, or services starts from within. Who creates these infrastructures,
products, or service offerings? Your development staff, team, or group(s). They also define the level of
security that protects your assets. We all need to create a sense of urgency across the entire IT
department. And, it starts with you.
</p>
<h3>Culture</h3>
<p>The culture of security is almost non-existent today. Early in my career the term DevOps did not exist. 
Network and development personnel were separated by the culture of the type of work they did.
Networks administrators and help-desk employees protected everything. They opened and closed
firewall ports. They enforced continual password changes. They required red-tape for employees that
forgot those seriously secure passwords. They lived and operated within a culture of distrust. "Why do
you need to change your password?'', they asked. "You already have firewall access to port 80. Why do
you need port 8080?'', would be the question. They live a lifestyle of distrust. It seemed respectable at
the time. Was the answer to security to choke the creativity of the development staff?
</p>
<p>The development staff would operate within a culture of creativeness. If it can be done, we'll do it. The
developers would figure out all the ways to bypass the in-place security practices and get the job done.
In many cases, these practices were unknown to the software development manager or director. This
culture still exists today within many organizations. DevOps is an attempt to place a trusted liaison
between the distrusting network folks and those flip-flop-wearing, loose-cannon developers. It sounds
promising. We now have a true mediating faction to resolve process conflicts between camps.
Discrimination between the cultures will now be non-existent. This is not my belief.
</p>
<h3>Proposal</h3>
<p>My proposal is a complement to DevOps. I propose we give the IT community one more acronym, and
in this case, called SCALE or Security Consideration and Lifestyle Exchange. I'm going to hereafter
refer to we as the shorts and flip-flops faction or software developers. We need to live a lifestyle of
security consideration from now until eternity or until spoofing, tampering, repudiation, disclosure,
denial of service, and elevation of privilege cease to exist, which ever comes first. The acronym
SCALE was purposely spelled scale to help with conceptual thinking within this new lifestyle. If we
don't always consider security vulnerabilities when we code, these inherent risks to the software, truly
scale within the code-bases to which we commit. Much of the software written today is owned by an
organization and not the individual developers. However, each developer needs to assume ownership of
the code that she develops. And, we also need to exchange education about security as we do our code
reviews and within any other discussions related to software development and security.
</p>
<p>If you are a homeowner, you probably lock the doors at night. You take care of your home and you
protect your investment. Your home is your shelter. It's safe and secure. I've had the mind-boggling
opportunity to work with developers from around the world that assumed no ownership whatsoever of
the code they were responsible for. That's ludicrous. This gives me the sense of urgency to correct this
problem even though it's not my responsibility. It makes me want to add the bullet - accountable for
the quality of your code to all these developer opportunities that ride the internet daily. Emails authored
by senior talent recruiters and technical companies, that provide talent to our enterprises, and do not
know what their clients really want in a software developer.
</p>
<p>We need to consider security with every project start, code review, and subsequent release of the
software. We should also do a threat model during the inception phase or just before we start
development. We should do another threat model just before the first release and also discuss the model
with each subsequent release. Security should be how we roll my friends. It should be our new
lifestyle. Whether the code belongs to you or your employer, it should be the best that it can be. That
depends on you solely.
</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>I hope that you will add SCALE or Security Consideration and Lifestyle Exchange right next to the
SDLC acronym in your minds. I also hope that you (we), the development community continue to
move in this direction. Make the consideration of security part of your personal process. Think of it as a
revolution. Don't rush the quality of your work. And, by all means, have it code reviewed. If you cheat
yourself on testing code coverage, at least let a cube-mate look at it when you're done.Be a listener and
learn from your seniors. Know that when you SCALE, your work doesn't add to the increasing risk of
security vulnerabilities with the growth of your software repositories.
</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Loyalty and Respect</title>
	  <link>//loyalty-and-respect</link>
	  <author>David L. Whitehurst</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-01-29T06:01:00-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//loyalty-and-respect</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	       <p>I've been using computing machines since about 1979. I'm a electrical/electronics engineer by education and software developer/programmer by trade. Sometime in the mid 1980's I convinced my superiors to allow me to push our wide area network to it utmost limits. We were using Windows then and the mainframe connectivity was already utilized to it potential and full capability. Windows was going to open the office and provide access to this complicated world of already communicating computing machines and let non-technical types into the very information we were gathering for them. Windows succeeded. Today, any square-headed citizen of the world, with a little money in his pocket, can purchase a computing machine and join the world of pointy-heads like me. But beware, you may not control this machine, it may control you.</p>

  <p>I pushed Windows NT 4.0 to its very limits on a 3D Computer Aided Design (CAD) project between about 1995 and 1998. Myself and my teammates wrote very complicated software with the expectation that it would run correctly on 4-processor sophisticated graphical workstation PCs. For the most part, our software performed exquisitely. Sometimes we had to put in bug tickets with Microsoft. And, we never got resolution to any problem submitted. We could only go as deep as the operating system would allow us to go. That was to what's called an application programming interface or API. And, this API had to be purchased. Anyone can program to this API but the tools and documentation had to be purchased. I'll oversimplify things, but e.g. a method might add two numbers together. We would call this method, sending 2 and 2 as inputs and the result would be 5. The documentation described what the method would do but the results were not what we expected. This is when I lost my respect for the Windows operating system. This was about 1997. And, most of my readers probably don't realize that somone allowed the illegal release of the OS to the public about that time. This why we have continual issues with malicious software like viruses and malware. This is also why there's a huge economy built on virus protection for Windows.</p>

  <p>Quite some time before my deep exposure to Windows NT, I had a $40,000 PC on my desk at work that ran some form of POSIX-based (UNIX) operating system. This OS was developed by some very smart people at ATT/Bell labs. I was writing programs to improve construction operations for making nuclear submarines. The machine I was given to use was very similar to the ones used to create Jurassic Park the movie. This OS was solid and performed as expected. The folks that developed it were not focused on corporate profit and mass-marketing. I respected the work of these individuals and still do today. A UNIX variant is available today called Linux and it's entire codebase is publicly available to anyone in the world (well, maybe some countries may be under export denial for security aspects). This truly open and solid operating system exists today with full disclosure of all of its source code. I have used it on many different computers (hardware), and I've never run a virus software or malware product except on my macbooks. The mac's OS-X uses some of a POSIX-based (UNIX) operating system architecture, however they install some of their own protections with the OS itself. I can truly say that I've not even come across a true UNIX/Linux virus protection software over the course of my career.</p>

  <p>I had lost my respect for Windows earlier not because I had to strip and re-install my Windows floppy disks every 3 months, but because the OS I used at work was not as solid as the one I used at home now. I was using Linux that I installed on a Toshiba laptop that came with Windows. And, I actually had the Linux code and compiled the OS myself custom to this laptop so the OS worked in every capacity and all of components of the laptop performed as expected. Pay close attention to the word expected. I now had a portable personal computer for writing any kind of machine instruction and if anything didn't work, I could dig in and find out why. I loved Linux then and stil do today.</p>

  <p>Throughout the years, I've worked for employers that have used Microsoft Windows for office machines and workstations. My dislike for Windows has always been the fact that the operating system has always been open to Microsoft but not the open-source community of developers around the world that govern themselves, their processes, their creations, and their actions. I purchased my first Apple product in 2007 when I started my own business because I couldn't find a job then. I loved it more than Linux because the hardware was exquisite and Linux was available to me again for work deep within Apple's OS-X. Yes, Apples are UNIX-like machines that can't run Windows natively. The catch comes with the fact that everything on the graphic-side of the Macintosh is proprietary to Apple including their hardware architecture. And, even though Apple has chosen not to use an open sub-system for it's graphics input/output (I/O), it's second to none in terms of quality and appeal to the public. So, I like Apple computers, but I can't say I love them. They beat the Windows computer where it comes to enjoyment and use of the machine. They cost more and rightly so because you get what you pay for. I can't love them yet because they are not true (POSIX) UNIX/Linux machines. OS-X contains pieces of the Berkley Software Distribution (BSD) which open and available to the public, however it's graphical system is written using Objective-C (UNIX uses C) and it came from a company called NeXT, formed by Steve Jobs. Apple owns the copyrights to this software currently.</p>

<p>My post is titled "Loyalty and Respect". This post is really not about loyalty and respect but about likes and dislikes of the operating systems I've had the priviledge of using. I also, haven't discussed Solaris or embedded operating systems even though I've written software to instruct some machines using these too. I kept my discussion to Windows, NIX, and Apple because loyalty and respect takes time. I've had quite some time to have respect for all three and still maintain my loyalty to Linux. Let's compare respect to liking something and loyalty to loving something. Like is a feeling and love is a promise. I like Windows, Apple, and Linux, but I truly love Linux. Several factors have brought me to these conclusions.</p>

<p>Before Christmas this past year, I purchased a very inexpensive Windows laptop. It came with Windows 10. I had accepted the use of Windows 7, hated Windows 8, and now I actually had a home computer with Windows 10 on it and liked it. As $250 compares to $2500, the windows laptop held its own compared to the macbook pros I've owned. I now had a new personal computer at home with Windows for the first time since 2007. Windows was off my dislike list again. My macbooks are used for most of my software development and I have recently installed the latest OS-X called El Capitan. Almost immediately I started with problems. My graphics display started locking periodically and then the machine wouldn't boot. I would start the computer and it would hang. I use a TimeMachine backup on a USB portable disk drive so I've been able to restore the machine. Apple led me through the restore the first time because the local restore was not acting as I expected. I had a few months without trouble because I've been using my Windows laptop for software development. I've generally loved my macbooks and I've shown my loyalty by purchasing lots of expensive software for them. That's changed. Let's say while I have great respect (like) for Apple and their promise to provide OS-X updates for free (providing you're at Snow Leopard or greater) they crossed a line with me when they 1) removed root access to parts of the filesystem and 2) changed their allowance of unsigned kernel extensions. Long story short, they affected that openness I've felt since the purchase of my first macbook pro. I've had 3 macbook pros but my brand loyalty is gone. I cannot promise anyone that my next laptop, tablet, or PC will be an Apple product.</p>

<p>In conclusion, this is why I respect (like) Windows, Apple, and Open-Source operating systems. I'll continue to show my loyalty to NIX systems because where I have the choice of OS, it will always be Linux or some form of UNIX variant. I love open-source software because I am not at the mercy of some company when something doesn't work right. I've been working on my newest (that's the irony) macbook pro for the last 2 days and I think that El Capitan has some little bug that's causing my kernel panics. I think they dropped one of their kernel extensions or modified one to include a model change in graphics cards maybe. I've been very angry about it so the proactive approach has been to write a blog post while the status bar on my macbook creeps along through another painful restoration. And, I can let everyone know that I actually like Windows 10. Good job Microsoft. And, thanks guys at Git for whipping us up a bash terminal using MINGW64. You rock! I'm not going to type the 3 letter dir when I can do the same thing with 2 and ls.</p>




	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
